good evening everyone uh i'll now call to order uh this april 1st 2025 meetings of committee of council uh mr harris can we please begin with the roll call of members yes madam president
mr med here mr arroyo here mr cleese here miss craig miss diaz here mr hirsch here president
baker here i expect counselor craig presently she is excused at this time um a few reminders for everyone at the top of the meeting good evening i ask that you please silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already and a reminder that this meeting and its participants are being recorded tonight we have meetings of committees of council there are no general public comment periods during this meeting however committee chairs will call for comments from the public for legislative items which means bills and resolutions that appear on the agenda comments and those times are limited to three minutes per speaker i must begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record i understand that there may be many of you in the room this evening to hear the report of to council during our public safety committee meeting i want to thank you all for being here and i also want to be clear that this report requested by council is informational and not legislative as i mentioned before and therefore there will not be public comment during our excuse me taken after that report before we begin committee meetings we have the first item on our agenda is the approval of the March 3rd 2025 committee meeting minutes motion to approve second we have a motion and a second on the minute so there any council comments on the minutes hearing none mr. Harris mr.
Mudd aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Cleese aye miss Diaz aye mr. Hirsch aye president
Baker aye all right our first committee meeting this evening is finance
council arroyo thank you council president uh we have three items on the agenda for this evening's committee meeting uh the first is the budget update for the year end of 2024 and the first quarter of 2025. i'd like to invite director campbell to come up for the budget update
good evening um so you have received a summary and a detailed budget report for both the year end of 2024 as well as the first two months of 2025 not quite the quarter because today is the first day of April March books are not yet closed so the latest month we have to report on is February we're gonna review both of these reports this evening though my main focus is going to be on the 2024 year-end report just as a little reminder per the home role charter where we will now start to provide you with monthly reports both the summary and the detailed written reports that you received this week because we need time to close the month we anticipate that you'll receive those reports from the previous month by the 20th of the following month so you would receive the March reports by April 20th and in addition we plan to present a budget update report such as this at a council committee meeting once per quarter because this process is new and really just beginning I welcome any feedback for what you would like to see in these reports in the future and how to make the process better we'll continue to refine it as we go so to the reports tonight I'd like to start with the 2024 reports as I said I'll mainly be be focused on those this evening I'm gonna speak from the summary reports that you received but I'm happy to answer questions or to take questions about the detailed reports as well I want to begin by saying that these are unaudited reports if you're familiar with audits you know that during audits their journal entries needed or other adjustments that may result in different numbers included in the final details of the budget but those are details and the numbers that you see this evening will remain approximately the same so overall we ended the year very well most of the departments and the enterprise funds ended the year better than budgeted in the general fund that's the first page of the summary report that you received you can see that our budget was approximately seventy three point four million for the year this is for the general fund not for the enterprise funds on the top of that page you'll see the revenue actual revenue is showing at about seventy one point three million or approximately two point one million less than we budgeted however this number is little bit deceiving as you're aware we must have a balanced budget in the general fund each year this is a this is a requirement and in order to do this sometimes we use cash reserves either as to show to show a revenue meaning that we're using some cash reserves to cover expenses or it shows on the expense side meaning that we're showing a surplus so we're putting money back into the cash reserves cash reserves are really the opposite of other lines so you want to see an expense and you don't want to see the revenue coming in it's my notes here so the original budget as I said of seventy three point four million included a transfer from cash reserves of approximately 2.3 million that was to cover expenses and our expenses from the general fund were approximately 2.2 million less than budgeted and some of our revenue in some of the other lines meaning in our mainly in our community planning areas exceeded budget so we did not need the cash reserves and ended the year with approximately 1.2 million in surplus that will go towards increasing our cash reserves most of the bureaus and the general fund came in under budget and this was due to variety of reasons but mainly savings from some staff staff vacancies that we had all of the departments worked very hard to cut expenses beyond those vacancies including using technology to figure out how to be more efficient which helped to adjust some some staffing levels as well in the enterprise funds three of the funds water stormwater and trash were budgeted to end the year in 2024 actually in a deficit and unlike the general funds this is allowable because these are enterprise or function as business funds the stormwater fund did end the year with a deficit but the deficit was approximately $400,000 less than budgeted so came in better better than budgeted the trash fund also ended with a deficit of approximately 70,000 more than budgeted however we have not yet received one grant which is the Act 101 recycling grant once that is received this deficit will be less but we don't know what that ending amount is so we didn't add that into this to this budget the water fund was budgeted to end with a deficit of approximately $860,000. The team, again, worked hard to reduce this over the year, and they actually ended with a slight surplus of $700,000. And the sewer fund was budgeted to end with a surplus of approximately $1.1 million. That was one of the four enterprise funds that was showing a surplus, mainly meant to build the cash reserve there. And we ended the year with a larger surplus of about $3.9 million. This really helps to establish an emergency fund in sewer, which we haven't had. I'll talk very briefly about the February 2025 reports before I stop for questions. It is really too early in the year to say much of substance about these reports. There aren't any notable items that are standouts at this time as there hasn't really been enough time in the year to see those trends for spending. However, I will note that some of the line items, if you're looking at the detailed lines, will look like they are already all spent. This is mainly due to encumbrances, which is really a hold that is put on funds for purchases that we know will happen at some point in the year, but it hasn't happened yet. So we've included these holds in the expense line because they will happen, but the cash might not have gone out of our accounts yet. And as we move through the year, these funds will be spent. So we're simply showing that spending from the beginning.
stop there and ask for questions thank you director Campbell open it up for any
questions from the committee if I may come 30s I have just one question there was a I believe ten million dollar grants for cities that may want if they're struggling in some area and that was by governor Shapiro are you aware that are you looking into that grant at all yeah i'm not sure which grant that that is you said it was for 10 million i think it was for 10 million it could be for more guys kind of took a quick glance of the the fact that it did came out i could also forward it to you yeah that that
would be great to see that thank you that's all i had any questions from full councilman
Thank you, Director Campbell. My question is, do we project that the revenues and taxes will meet the budget for Q1? I know it's still a little bit too early to say, but are we on pace from a revenue side?
We are. So again, it is a little bit too early in the year to talk about, but one of the things that happens is real estate taxes are collected at the beginning of the year so those are those are coming in now we'll see those it you know increase especially through June here so yeah at this point everything's coming in as we have planned in fact some of the revenue again in the community planning lines it's coming in a bit higher than we had we had projected thank you
and um it's good to see that you know some of the losses we projected were not as heavy if you were able to mitigate some of those expenses um do we project that those expenses will continue to see that trend in 2025 as the year goes on will we be able to continue to mitigate some of
these expenses that's our goal um um yeah i mean we never quite know how the year is gonna gonna
to turn out but we're always looking to decrease expenses if we can so when you
say last year you mean 2024 yes okay so it's about 1.2 million and that'll be returned to the or that that's a surplus to go into the cash reserves we're anticipating about well over two million this year because of the earned income tax increase and a lot of that as we talked about in the budget process is really to try to increase the cash reserves because we feel like they haven't been at a good level for emergencies that might come up
piggyback off of that um what's the recommended percentage for our reserve fund um so it varies
based on municipality um we are trying to get between 15 and 20 percent and that's up the budget of the operating annual operating budget yeah thank you any other questions or comments
from council thank you for the uh thank you for the uh budget update um we'll move on to the uh Second item on the agenda, which is administration resolution number 25 2025 amending the capital improvement plan
Just stay here for this one, so The other director Campbell is handing out some updated project Details for this so you would have received this list already in the In the committee packet, but this gives a few updates to the project status which is the last column in those wanted to give you some of that so that you can see which projects have been completed and and how that has been adjusted so these I'm gonna talk about these both of them yes please thank you I'm gonna talk about both of these together that's what I was actually just getting ready to say it's two different resolutions one for the 2018 bonds and those the 2018 bonds is the sewer fund and then one for the 22 bonds those are the water funds so yeah as capital projects are completed or our need adjustments once the actual work on the project begins we need to make shifts within line-item allocations in each bond fund to accommodate these adjustments and most of these adjustments require approval of the amendment from Council and that's what we're bringing to you this evening this is a regularly occurring process so you've received these changes in years past we we did another one of these in March 2024 at the Finance Committee meeting it's not allocating any more money but rather it's a request to move money between the already approved projects it's very hard to estimate exact costs for projects and bonds, as many of the projects take many years to complete. So this allows us to close out projects that may have come in under budget and move funding to other projects that were already approved that may need more funding. So again, two different plans that require adjustments, or two different bonds that require adjustments, and therefore two different resolutions. So for the 2018 bond funds, which 20 resolution 25 2025 we have a number of shifts that are that are occurring in the the line items there the shifts total about 2.3 million you see all of the details in the 2018 go or general obligation bond exhibit a and those are all projects as I mentioned connected to the sewer funds these there's no new projects proposed in this 2018 bond fund financing so all of these projects have already been approved in previous council meetings for the 2022 bond funds which is resolution 26 2025 we also have a number of shifts that are needed between the projects as some are completed and others need additional financing those shifts total about 5.3 million and those details again are all included in the 2022 go bond exhibit a that you received and those projects again are all connected to the water fund when the 2022 bond funds were approved by council the approval was for there was approval for administration to transfer funds within certain categories so the transfers that you see in this exhibit this resolution 26 2025 are from one one of those categories to another um so the two categories in the water fund are from the transmission and distribution and work at the two plants the conestoga and sesquihanna plants and in addition to these transfers we're actually requesting two new projects to be added for the conestoga plant both of those are related to membranes at the conestoga which are the treatment technology there and i think i will We'll stop there.
I'll open it up for questions from the committee. Councilor Caliz.
Thank you, Councilor Arroyo. Thank you, Director Campbell, for the presentation. And are there any projects being delayed or canceled or reduced as a result of this amendment?
No, they're not being delayed. I am not aware of any being reduced. Director Campbell's shaking his head no. So no, I don't think any of them are being reduced either.
you any additional questions or comments from council i'll just um mention one thing if i
may counselor rayo is that when you look at the phase three large um tnd susquehanna river to water treatment plant um that is the design phase that's been completed um we're now in phase three and that's where the penvest uh financing that we were talking about related to this most recent bond um that's the project that some of these bond funds are going to go to so and we need additional to complete that and i'll also just say that um you know the expense of buying steel pipe uh is changing and that may impact um how much uh replacement we're going to be able to do but that 42 inch main replacement is significant and a major focus um for for this year and we'll be
talking a bit more about it in the public works committee as well yeah great thank you mayor
sorachi um any questions from the public this would be in regards to either resolution 25 or 26.
starting bird and street once again i'm going to ask council why they do not put this information up on the screen that you're showing we spend a lot of money updating city this city council chambers with technology and yet you're talking about things that we're not able to see it's not available on the website at this time and it needs to be put out to the public one of the reasons when i was on the home rule and suggested even about the reports was that so the public would but have more information, not just the council members. So again, I'm asking council, hoping to get an answer, why this is not presented to the public so we can see what she's referring to or what anyone's referring to when they're presenting something.
Thank you. Tony D'Astra, 700 Block New Holland Avenue. I want to echo what Darlene's saying. Municipal government is where we as the people supposed to understand how government functions on all levels. This is the smallest level, so this is the school. And years ago, I was encouraged that, you know, if I want to see the work actually get done, I need to go to the committee meetings, and that's why I started live broadcasting the committee meetings as well as city council. So I do feel that Darlene's right on the money, like these materials should be prepped and prepared and presented on the screen, because even when you're viewing from home which I've done recently a few times all you see is the agenda it's not really an educational experience for the residents it's just noise on a screen so it really is imperative to the public that these get prepared and presented thank you
and I think we could present these as well I think these are presented on the website prior to council meetings and prepared for public availability hi I'm
Brian Nelson Columbia Avenue I just had one question you mentioned the vacancies that you were using to like we're saving money off of the vacancies are there any plans to fill those vacancies or you're just gonna leave like not hire for these positions what's the plan going forward with the vacancies that you guys mentioned oh was that for the budget oh I apologize I think I miss misinterpreted that but yeah yeah so I guess I mean going forward I guess for like you know talking about the budget and stuff like that are we budgeting in for 2025 to
fill these vacancies or is that not going to be budgeted in yeah so many of
the vacancies that happened in 2024 were included in the budget for 2025 but many of them weren't like full vacancies it was people that had left positions so there might have been a gap in filling that position before another person came
in Susie Gomez 100 block the north for a divorce Street. I just wanted to implement for the public, not so much for you guys. What Janet had mentioned, $10 million of the Josh Shapiro fund that was granted to municipalities should have been used. As Tina Campbell mentioned, she's relying on the income tax increase from the taxpayers that was granted for the homeroom charter. So when you're looking at a budget, I think that all of these factors should come into play, especially when you're trying to balance a budget and you have deficits. It's important to utilize the grants that is given to especially crisis areas or for municipalities that deal with issues in the community that the government is releasing funding for. Who writes these grants, Tina? why is it not important for you to you know push a little bit further into looking into these grants because 10 million dollars is a lot of money that could have been used for these areas and for it to be ignored is beyond my understanding any further public comment
all right as it pertains to resolution number 25 uh i will motion to move resolution number 25 to next full council meeting all those in favor i'm going to uh resolution number 26 and i'll motion to move resolution number 26 to the next full council meeting second we have a second all those in favor aye move council council president that concludes the finance committee meeting
thank you very much uh now we'll move to our public safety committee meeting councillor yes
I just wanted to first inform everyone that, just like President Veque said, there will be no comments during the time that Chief Mendez is doing his presentation. There has been some drastic changes, and I picked that up when Councilor Arroyo ran the budget meeting where there was no comments from the public, which was very odd because for years there was. and at that time there were written comments that were submitted although I think someone needs to look to see why it has not been updated but I would like Chief Mendez to please come and speak
to the public thank you very much all right good evening everyone thanks for having me so first I'd like to start off with a little bit of the training that your police department does you know as I've stressed numerous times over the years Lancaster City has one of the best trained police departments around and we dedicate a lot of our time to training. Some of those and I guess you guys are getting a packet which I'm going to summarize off of and read as well. Some of those trainings include control tactics which are defensive tactics arrest procedures and subject control de-escalation techniques these are techniques resolved to resolve conflict peacefully we train in mental health awareness understanding and assisting individuals in crisis and bias training and dress addressing implicit and explicit bias in policing some of the specialized training areas our officers go through our advanced patrol officer certifications those cover safety priorities, decision-making, and patrol tactics. We require yearly use of force trainings. These trainings include, again, decision-making, control tactics, de-escalation principles, and post-incident care. And one of the trainings we really focus on is reality-based scenarios. These are done to enhance decision-making, verbal skills, and de-escalation techniques as well. That's a lot of our internal training that we go through. The Bureau also does a lot of external training programs, some of which include crisis intervention team certification, the art of reading people, trauma-informed training, which we partnered with our social workers on, and the entire police department went through that training, and we continue to train that as well. Along with those trainings, we're mandated through MOPEC, which is the certifying police agency for the Commonwealth we do yearly updates that are required again by MoPEC some of those again mental health first aid use of force and de-escalation tactical communication understanding stereotypes bias critical decision-making models the overall key principles are those our ethics values proportionality and the sanctity of human life and again these are all mandated through the state your police department has a commitment to training we mandate 16 hours of training a year that they have to go through that's mandated again they take an additional training as well and one thing we're really proud of with your your officers is to show you how dedicated they are since January of 2024 they have conducted over a hundred and 50 hours of training on their own time. They come in. They volunteer to come in. They work with training instructors before shift, middle of the day, on weekends. This is uncompensated time that they spend to make themselves better at doing their job, and we're really proud of that for the amount of work the officers put in. Again, like I stated, we do a lot of external trainings. CIT is probably one of the biggest ones and just be sure that your your police department is committed to getting better as I've said numerous times no one's perfect but I will say this you have one of the best police departments around and we're committed to training and getting better all right now I'll move on to I think what everyone's here for our use of force report and reporting procedures the police department likes to police officers may They only use force when it is objectively reasonable, proportional, and necessary given the totality of the circumstances. These circumstances include, but are not limited to, force necessary to effect an arrest, control an individual, lawfully detain a subject, prevent escape, or to protect themselves or others. We have a use of force policy that's been on our website since 2022. I would recommend everybody read it thoroughly. There's a lot of information in there. There's definitions. There's a lot on our website, and, again, it's been there since 2022. Officers will follow a use-of-force continuum, which is a guideline. It will show subjects' resistance as well as officers' reactions and what they can do to overcome that resistance. So I'd like to point out that the degree of force used depends on what the officer perceives as reasonable and necessary under the circumstances, the Bureau expects an officer to employ only the force necessary to accomplish a lawful arrest. I wanted to break down some levels of resistance for everyone. Again, as the continuum we use is like a book, it'll have levels of resistance and our levels that will use force. Officers can enter at any level. It it depends on the what the subject is presenting them but we do like to start and and if possible work our way up as we go through that levels of resistance which is in our use of force policy but I want to touch on a couple things psychological intimidation is the first level that can be circling an officer surrounding them it can be inciting a crowd to come around them it can be the thousand yards there where they're staring through you we train our officers on you know keys to recognize it could be clenched fists body blading those are all psychological intimidation next would be verbal non-compliance this would be the subject direct refusal they could be arguing stalling you know basically they're not cooperating verbally next level would be passive resistance the subject is either sitting or lying down it can be their refusing to let go of something scenario with that would be a steering wheel on the vehicle sometimes subjects that don't want to get arrested will hold on
to a steering wheel so that would be that level after that the next would be
defensive resistance that can include fleeing you know they're fleeing the officers it can be pulling away refusing to be handcuffed and then next would be active aggression that would be delivering strikes you know hitting an officer kicking an officer actively assaulting an officer and then lastly on that would be deadly force that would be where the officer believes his or her life or the life of a citizen is in in jeopardy with the life of down and typically those would be a knife a gun it can be you know many things that would call serious bodily injury or death levels of control so again as I said it's a we use like a book format so I went over that all use of force starts out with officer presence at a scene that's considered a use of force most times and as we get into stats a little bit later the mere presence of an officer in uniform will get the results they want and and it's you don't have to go past that level the next level an officer can use would be verbal direction those are commands you're under arrest don't move put your hands behind your back verbal commands after that would be soft empty hands control these are control techniques they can be joint locks you know any movement that any way you want to control movement and we also have OC spray in that level of control from there it would be hard empty hand control those are strikes to a person those they're hard empty hand control because they have a higher higher probability of injury to the officer or the subject being arrested moving on from there would be the intermediate weapons level that would be impact weapons a baton or taser falls under that that that level of of control as well from there lastly would be deadly force and again that would be the officer fears for his or her life for the life of a community member or citizen that they have to protect and take immediate action so I want to just you know touch on you know everything that you know is in our use of force policy our guidelines are guidelines under title 18 chapter 5 general principles of justification everything we do is based on whether it's crimes code case law best practices in policing touch a little bit on de-escalation so when safe and feasible to do again given the totality of circumstances officers shall attempt to take action to to prevent or decrease the need to use force during an incident such techniques we use our persuasion advice providing warnings prior to using force that can be as simple as you're under arrest trying to talk to them rather than have to use any type of force establish a rapport when possible engage in communication evaluating whether the you can use time distance or positioning and when appropriate request additional resources one key thing with de-escalation is it requires time and distance and also not everybody can be de-escalated there's things that factor into whether you can de-escalate somebody or not also I'd like to point out we do have a duty to intervene policy so if an officer sees excessive force force that would fall outside of our policies and procedures and standards they are required under
our policy to intervene when they see that all right next I'd like to move
into reporting a little bit and again our that policy is on our website to show reporting requirements we have a separate policy for documenting use of force incidents so officers shall complete a police bureau use of force report prior to the end of their shift so if they meet one of these uh these marks uh we require them to report that doc finish that document before their their shift ends so before they go home for the evening or day they have to get that paperwork done uh some of the you know the the list we of when they would need to do a use of force i'm going to go through because i think it's really important anytime a person has been physically struck by an officer anytime a chemical agent is used against a person so anytime oc spray is used we do a use of force report anytime a conductive electronic weapon is used so that would be the taser if that's used they have to do a report any impact weapon is used if a firearm is pointed in the direction of a person so when you look at some of our stats which we'll get into the deadly force stats it may look like they're higher we require any time a handgun is used if they're clearing a building somebody pops whatever reason and they pointed in their direction we require them to do reporting on that as well anytime a canine bites a person so if canine is engaged with someone and bites them we require a report any injuries that are visible to the officer or complaint of injuries anytime someone complaints about the force so if it's a an arrest that you know doesn't necessarily meet the standard but somebody complains when they're being arrested that force was too much will require a use of force if anyone requests medical treatment for an injury they they say happened you know even if it appears to be an older injury and they're saying no it happened now will require officers do reports we have a couple caveats in there that any supervisor can mandate an officer do one so if a supervisor is that a call or or you know for whatever reason they can mandate an officer does that and also if an officer just feels like they they they should do one so um if they're like well you know i didn't really didn't really meet the level of any of our standards but i i think i should do one then then they can do that as well touch a little bit on the review procedures for those um so i know i mentioned this before but I'd like to point out again that when we review use of force reports, it's a 1989 case law. I'd really recommend if anyone's interested in use of force and policing that you spend some time and review the case law of Graham v. Connor. And what came out of that case was the objective reasonable standard. And I think the simplest way to put it is we have to view it through the lens of the officer at that time. with the same training same you know if the same exact location what they're witnessing at that time we can't come back and Monday morning quarterback and say well you should have thought of this like we have to put ourselves in that officer's shoes at that time what a reasonably trained officer would do and met with the same circumstances that's the guidance of it and again that's a 1989 Supreme Court ruling that has withstood the test of time since then so our review procedure like I said the officer does it at the beginning of his shift his or her shift or at the end of his or her shift it then goes to the officer in charge so that is typically a lieutenant who oversees that platoon of officers that officer that lieutenant is required to read all reports make sure they're done accurately, review all body camera footage and car camera footage. And then if any corrections may need or if there's any issues, they can address it there. After the officer in charge reviews it, it gets sent to our training cadre. It's a group of officers that are trained that conduct our training and review all of our use of force reports. They're the officers that are certified to conduct the training that we train throughout the year. From there, the training sergeant will, I'm sorry, from there, the training sergeant will assign it to a group and a training cadre member will review it. They will, again, read all reports, view all video, make sure it falls within our training and our policies and procedures. And again, just to point out, at any level of this somebody reviewing it can raise an alarm and say hey I don't think this is right or I think there's an issue with the training after it goes through the training training cadre it then gets assigned to the appropriate division captain so typically you know if it's a use of force done by a patrol officer the patrol captain gets that report saying if a detective uses force a detective detective captain will get that that captain again reviews all reports body camera footage gets the input of the training cadre whether it meets the the standards or not if there were any issues what they were what the training cadre recommends and then after the captain approves it it gets forward to the chief of police for another final review again review all reports all video see if there's any issues look at any remarks made by training cadre and at any point along this process our internal affairs can can step in and look at it as well if they don't for you know whatever reason once I'm done with it I send it to them for the last final review and then entered into our system as final so that's the process for review just wanted to touch a little bit on you know if there are issues that come up obviously we can you know if there if there's a issue we can we can discipline but some of the levels will do with discipline would be it could be a training issue that we need to retrain we could have to do coaching I think the easiest way to describe coaching is if the officers force was correct they had every reason to use it but there were other options that we would like them to look at we can we can do a coaching for them internal review investigation policies again if there's any violations of that we can move on to disciplinary action as well annually each supervisor shall ensure that their personnel review applicable law and provisions of this policy the review shall be documented and retained retained within the police bureau records if you're carrying any weapon you have to certified in it and trained yearly and we maintain those records as well all
right I think if we can move on to some stats now all right so the first stats
we have are calls for service resulting in arrest and as you can see the larger block the color is not the best on this screen but the bottom larger block is the calls for service with no arrest moving on from there it's arrest not requiring force so you make an arrest and it doesn't rise to a level of you know requiring a force a use of force report and from there is the arrest requiring force that's the line on top of those and just I'll just do quarter four for example out of eight thousand six hundred and ninety eight calls for service, 477 arrest, 29 of those required a use of force report for one reason or another. So those are those data as you can see. Next is all incidents of force, non-physical incidents of force versus physical incidents of force. Again, a non-physical incident of force would be something that did not require the use of force reporting. You know, and as we talked about in our use of force continuum. Even officer presence is a use of force verbal command, so if those would be the arrests under that data, then followed by the physical incidents of force. Next one. All incidents of force by type breaks it down a little simpler as we talked about. As you can see, officer presence, verbal direction, all the way up to deadly and again I just want to make sure everyone's clear on the deadly force it's not that deadly force per se was used it's that if you know if you pointed a gun in the direction of somebody we require that to be a report so that would generate that that number as well all right moving on to some progress from you know the Bureau again in 2018 body cameras and revised our use of force policy our social worker program has been a tremendous asset for the police and the community as I stated in the training all our officers have gone through trauma-informed training you know our recruitment and our recruitment and hiring efforts as well and something we're real proud of is our Pleiac accreditation process it's been about two years I think it felt like 20 at times but again that was going through a rigorous process a review of all our policies procedures are how we operate our equipment and I think it's 139 points that we pull proofs for and why we're almost there April 24th we have our we go for the official meeting to hopefully be an accredited agency it just doesn't stop at April 24th we're continuing to work this is a never-ending process with accreditation and pulling proofs changing policies making sure they fit the most recent best practices for policies and standards. Less than 1% of calls for service result in use of force. Again, our police social worker program has served hundreds of residents. We're really proud of the community engagement office with Sergeant Todd Greger and all the work he's done for the community engagement. He's really taken it to a whole other level. we partner with blueprints we do ride-alongs with them target those in need for addiction recovery we have a partnership with benchmark for our youth intervention and increased youth crime prevention efforts through engagement and our SROs as well we get a lot of compliments on our school resource officers and we're extremely proud of the work they do a lot of it goes unnoticed you might not see it or hear about it but the relationships they're building with students in the school district has been tremendous and we're extremely proud of that as well okay some youth gun seizures since 2018 as you can see you know it's been increasingly alarming I know we've talked about it at least since 21 when I was patrol captain we're seeing an increase in our youth carrying firearms and you can see the stats there I think you know what stands out a lot is you know from 24 and younger the amount of guns that we're seeing year-to-date youth gun seizures as you can see there is 17 currently and those are the age groups for the year so far so we're on pace again and it's a number that you know we would like to see be zero and lastly with the stats again youth gun seizures for 18 and under you can see the age groups with that as well and again it's it's alarming and it's something that you know we really need to fix as a community but we need everybody to to help with that and that is by year going back to 2018 my stats person just wanted me to make sure you okay and that's all I have and you have any questions for me I'd be happy to try and answer them
First, the most recent incident that most people are here for with the March 2nd, given that this involved minors, is there a separate use of force policy and is there a separate reporting standard when it involves minors?
So our use of force policy is the same and our reporting is the same for any individual with as far as our reporting for use of force.
And then when there is use of force and the reports, the findings, how do residents currently access them? And are there ways that we can make it more accessible for residents?
So I believe they're currently quarterly. We're putting out our stats quarterly on our website with the use of force data. So that's been on. And I think it's, do we go back a few years with that one that's currently on? So it's on our website and quarterly.
Accessibly. Not the reports. Only quarter fours. Well, given that these are quarterly, can we have request reports quarterly to the council, similar to the finance quarterly reports, to kind of go over the use of force within the quarter and the findings? Would that be something that council could request by the court?
As far as the stats, or I'm not sure what you're doing. I'm sorry, I'm in trouble hearing you with the background.
What incidents happened within this quarter? What were the findings and just a report to counsel?
Similarly, given it's not a report to counsel. I don't see an issue with that as why we couldn't do that. Yes.
My last question is, given that you stated that the review is viewed in the lens of an officer that is fully trained, is there any consideration in if this officer had previous incidents or his past or anything like that?
So that's two different questions. We view each incident on its own standing and merit. So that's the first part of the answer, I guess I would say. Now, if an officer violates a use of force policy or any policy for that matter, then we use other violations to increase discipline. And our discipline is covered under the collective bargaining agreement, which we're bound by as well. So again, each incident, we have to view for the incident. I'll also add, because that's a very good question, the way we track our stats in the system we use, we have early intervention alerts. So we set it. If the mark is set and an officer reaches that for numerous different things, not just use of force, if they get to that level, all supervisors, internal affairs, get an alert and it'll say like you know hey officer so-and-so had six use of force reports in this time frame it needs a second look and then we we require supervisors and IAA to look into that and see if there's a pattern of something there and it's not just use of force we do that for vehicle pursuits complaints there's level there's thresholds and if they meet that then we review it. We also do random body cam reviews so we have supervisors randomly pulling up body camera footage to review the officers as well and again those are accreditation standards that we have to meet continually as well.
Is there anyone else?
Thank you, Councilor Diaz. Thank you, Chief Mendez, for the presentation. uh what immediate steps is the department willing to take in order to increase transparency and
rebuild the public choice what steps are we willing to take yes i mean transparency and we build public trust well i think public trust is a two-way street like you know we have to work as
well if you have to come to the table and we have to talk so we we will meet
people where they're at as I said about our community engagement office that was created in you know I forget the year but the past few years the work they've done has been tremendous the accreditation process was an outside agency or an outside entity reviewed from all across the state we don't know these people they come in they they they reviewed they looked at everything or we put our stats on online you know we're mill again we're willing to do everything but again you know we would welcome people's involvement as well we have the citizen police academy we're going to launch again i would i would love to see that packed we tried to do it last year and it we didn't have enough people interested so come to citizen police academy we will tell you how we do things we will put you through scenarios i would open that up to every council member as well uh any future city leader uh any community member come our doors are open we will have it um i think we're shooting for a june time frame I hope it's so packed that we have to run three this year or more So there are limitations and I believe the mayor is going to talk about that in a report she has I think it's great, but I mean, we're a city of 60,000 people. I think it's great. Can there be improvement? There can always be improvement. I've never said the police are perfect. We're perfect. But the strides we came from 2018, I'd really even say from like 2021 or 2022 to now, has been tremendous. Everybody up here should be proud of their police department. The community should be proud of their police department. They work tirelessly. we're the shortest we've ever been but our clearance rate on crimes is amazing the engagement from our community engagement office the hours that they put in the SROs the events that go unnoticed where they're volunteering their time to go spend time with our youth I'll go to the engagement office again on his own time going in playing basketball with youth our officers are doing a tremendous job
thank you
no further question thank you yes if i may she was going to speak first i have one question um i want to just clarify on the the latest update of statistics for use of force in the most recent quarter that's available just to put it in perspective so that was the slide and it's available on the police website 86 8 698 arrests and the the use of force on the continuum that's reportable is 29 point zero zero three percent of arrest I just wanted to make
sure that number is correct so the eight thousand six hundred ninety eight are calls for service with no arrest yes then the next level up would be the arrest not requiring force followed by the arrest reporting great force thank
you I wanted to get clarification on that that is still point zero six percent
of the arrest so thank you thank you councillor ds um thank you for the report i appreciate it um a couple questions uh regarding to one of the things you mentioned was um after an incident happens um you mentioned the case law that occurred well what type of coaching happens after or does any coaching happen after when there's an incident of what improvements could have been made with the officer um i know you said you know there's no monday morning quarterbacking but are there ways of coaching officers on alternative approaches etc during an incident so yeah and when I was talking about some
of the the post review things that we can do coaching and again coaching is typically used where they didn't violate a policy but we're saying hey do better you can do this this is a better option I can think of one you know coaching recently where we like when practical we tell you to make sure they know you're going you're under arrest tell them they're under arrest we had an officer not do that arrested the person we see that they didn't do anything wrong the person was to be arrested but we coached them and said hey like you had the opportunity to tell them they were under arrest that needs to happen now if that pattern were to continue with an officer and luckily it has not with that officer then it would move on to another level of discipline I believe
in 2018 is when we first started having body cams or having every officer wear body cams can you tell us a little bit more about the policy and the practice for police officers and body cams as far as when they're turned on when the
footage is reviewed yes so we have a we have a specific policy just geared around body camera so I would have I didn't bring that with me to really get into it but it's the it's on all the time we have a feature activated on it where I think it's like up to 18 hours if they don't have it on now that we can pull back and do it so there's just some changes we made recently with it the technologies have grown which now allows us to do stuff like that but it should be on when they're interacting with the public that being said again we're human so sometimes officers will be in the heat forget to turn it on that would be a policy violation that gets addressed through that means of the
policy so they are not co-responders they don't
respond to the call they do a lot of you know work beforehand so they they review the calls they see the patterns of the places we're going to they have a little bit more access to some of the history with some of the members in our community so they will do outreach that way but they will also you know if an officer requests them officer gets to a scene makes it it's safe where they can enter if it's a need for a social worker then they will respond to that but they're not they're not out there just responding before a scene safe so I'll
just start by saying that you know during my time as mayor i did not always have full trust for confidence in the police bureau and nor did they in me that has changed at least i know that i have confidence in our police bureau and i believe that we have made a lot of strides i'm proud of their work and the work underway and that progress has been a journey for sure and i recognize that some will support these efforts and some may not when i speak to residents across the city i do hear a clear message they want a fully staffed police bureau you you are well aware that we are down quite a number of officers they want our officers present in their neighborhoods and they want safe streets i want to clarify a point of discussion this has come up from several of you related to a civilian review board so just to be perfectly clear the city of lancaster has never had a civilian review board instead during my time as mayor from 2018 to 2024 we have had a community and police working group this has not been a formal board commission or authority um this group has played played a valuable role in strengthening those community relationships informing policy changes early on identifying leadership qualities for a new police chief and improving recruitment strategies they also have participated in events like national night out neighborhood month block parties you may have been you may have seen them wearing t-shirts and over time the police bureau has institutionalized community engagement practices through the office of community engagement and i think you heard chief mentioned that so last year the working group merged with the call to action committee that's led by the school district of lancaster that group meets monthly with school staff youth serving organizations city representatives from multiple departments and others and an area of focus one area of focus is on youth gun violence prevention and that I reported on to council in February related to the PCCD grant that they received through the city I have not supported establishing a civilian review board because they lack authority existing review boards in Pennsylvania are purely advisory police disciplinary processes are governed by collective bargaining agreements just as they are with every other union contract in the city and across the state other concerns include legal liability and the fact that evidence in criminal cases falls under the jurisdiction of the district attorney's office and that limits what can be shared externally if the goal is to build trust between the community and police I do not believe a civilian review board is effective without authority they create mismatched expectations between the community board members and the police bureau however I do see value and external validation of police policies and practices and this is why you've been hearing so much about the accreditation process it has been a priority for me and chief Mendez this was something that I have been wanting to do since 2018 and under chief Mendez leadership we are getting there and you will continue to hear more about this in the next month regarding body camera footage the city strictly adheres to state laws governing its release including act 22 the juvenile act and the criminal history record information act these laws ensure the integrity of of criminal proceedings and the protection of minors so i understand community concerns about police interactions with young people it is difficult to see youth fighting in public parks and then be pepper sprayed however every individual got home safely and that's something that we should not take for granted personally as a mom i will never forget attending the funeral of a 16 year old who was stabbed in june 2019 in a street fight the anguish in that church sanctuary stays with me the march march 2nd arrests were also difficult to witness however the individuals that were involved broke the law were repeatedly warned they fled from police and they were subsequently arrested last saturday i received a video from a personal resident that's just a city resident of the same group on their bikes including one of their recently arrested teens riding recklessly on orange street near the exit of the prince street garage blocking traffic and surrounding cars addressing unsafe behavior among young bike riders is not about blame it's about recognizing a real issue many residents have encountered this group firsthand and then express their concern and their frustration if we all want our kids to get home safely and to limit police interactions with young people whenever possible then we need other solutions as such we remain committed to working with the school district Boys and Girls Club benchmark the mix and others to foster those positive relationships with young people and I encourage everyone to invest similarly i'll close with this your police bureau and your city remain committed to public safety in every neighborhood and on every block public safety is a partnership between the police bureau and the community your bureau your police chief who grew up in this city south queen street and myself are dedicated to that partnership and will continue to strengthen it with city residents who are committed to the same thank you for the opportunity to add my comments to the chief's report and that is all I have to
say right now Thank You mayor sir Archie I also want to extend a thank you for chief Mendez to take that opportunity to come and give us the information and stats of what is going on in our community in reference to crime as well as unfortunately children that are carrying weapons that can cause damage not only to themselves but others and that right now concludes everything for safety committee Thank You Amanda Thank You councillor Diaz we will move now to
our Public Works Committee councillor Hirsch Thank You council president Public Works Committee has five items on the agenda tonight they're all for the most part administrative in nature council president I may give a minute for some
folks to sure as directors Campbell approached the yeah I was gonna say
favorite plural way to say it why why that's happening can I just kept follow up with councillor Diaz about the funding that you mentioned councillor yeah I did find it this is a proposal from the Shapiro administration to add ten million dollars to the budget that is currently being considered it would add money to the special state fund that aids Lake local governments facing severe economic hardships in its proposed budget for the 2025-26 fiscal year this would help support communities under the Municipal Financial Recovery Act also known as Act 47 which gives municipalities that declare financial distress access to these resources so it this is I'm reading from a news article from March 24th so it sounds like this is in a budget proposal from the Shapiro administration and obviously we'll we'll pay attention to that moving forward and I'll just say like it's very frustrating that that money would only be eligible for cities who are entering Act 47 which we are not very much on purpose correct
yes I agree and I was looking at the same thank you
councillor yes back to Public Works no no that was a good that was a good information to add in there and it's all kind of related I think or at least it was coming from the conversation we were having earlier which is about upgrades to our water infrastructure so in relation to resolution 27 all I see
director Stephen Campbell at the stand thank you very very much I will introduce the the pieces that we want to talk about in the following way the city has talked about some about the pen best loans recently as a reminder pen best is Pennsylvania State Revolving Loan Fund. They provide funding for certain water, sewer, and stormwater projects. While they offer a few grant options, most of their funding is in the form of very low interest loans. We pursue this funding in place of bond funding as the projects qualify to take advantage of the lower loan rates. On March 3rd, Tina Campbell mentioned that we will be going after Penvest financing for some sewer and water projects that are eligible for Penvest. Penvest requires resolutions for us to submit an application, so these resolutions tonight are for the submission of the application. They are not to accept loan funding. These applications will be submitted in one of the Penvest application cycles in 2025. There are three resolutions regarding Penvest this evening, but they relate to only two Penvest applications. The first resolution this evening, 27-2025, is for the continued work on lead line replacement. We are actually pursuing some grant funding on this application and we have to write the application as a loan application, but there is grant funding available for this work, so we are pursuing that with this application. The application for 27-2025 is in the amount of 1.709338 million, which represents approximately 108 lead water service lines for Lancaster City. These are the lines that we've already identified and or with a little bit of reconfirmation need to be reconfirmed. we do what we call potholing to make sure that there that they require replacement that 1.7 represents approximately six thousand to twenty thousand dollars per line depending on the circumstance and by going after this low interest funding we would prohibit or we would make sure that the property owner is not on the hook for having to pay for that lead line replacement We are in the process right now of having done approximately, identified approximately 25 to 27 percent of the lead lines in the city of Lancaster, or of the lines in the city of Lancaster, and we're about to have what we call machine learning, an upload of machine learning information within the next couple of months that hopefully would increase that percentage to about 75 percent of the 60 to 75 percent. 5% of the lines to be known or not known. But over the course of the next two to three years, we are still going to be continuing to confirm the inventory of service lines that need to be replaced because they're lead or other. So this particular request is to seek the ability to make the application for the 1.7 million in low interest loans from Penvest.
thank you director campbell and i'll just add um that you know part of the confirmation process pennsylvania is one of uh four states that is requiring or the dp in this case is requiring two forms of confirmation correct so that's part of what adds to the additional the cost
and the consternation of having to do this work yes yeah um are there any public works
committee comments on our resolution 27 or comments or questions from full
council thank you dr. Campbell I was trying to take some notes you mentioned that this would cover how many approximately what about 108 service
lines that means the that means the reconfirmation the excavation the removal and the replacement of those lines uh and there we because we are pretty certain of which which these lines are we know that some of them require a lot of excavation there's a lot of stone work there's a lot of and then the replacement of the sidewalks etc so that you
don't have an unfinished situation when it's completed and just to put a finer point on it the funds would cover the total cost of that where in other circumstances in other cases outside of this project property owners would be uh responsible for the total cost of it that is
correct thank you uh counselor thank you thank you thank you director campbell uh what is the budgetary impact on this additional debt service the budgetary impact on the lead service line
replacement this is this is perhaps the the lowest way the lowest priced or lowest cost way that we can get this work done it is a low interest loan it does need to be repaid but it is by being a low interest loan over time it minimizes or reduces the impact as much as practical is that to say that it eliminates it no there are there's still a lot of work that still has to be done to confirm over the course of the next several years the number of lines that do require replacement um and it is it basically an unfunded mandate that we need to find we as a municipality as as every municipality in this country of the united states has to find the ways of replacing the lead service lines And as of the date, a date in early or mid-2023, the cost of that is, the cost of lines that fall under this mandate will not be borne by the particular property owner.
Thank you. And on the contrary, does that mean, should we be getting more, should we be going after more dollars through this law?
It's a very good question, and we've tried several different ways of doing this. there are two challenges one challenge is that every time you make this application or in the earlier programs there's there's an administration fee that attaches to making that application and so the higher number of applications we make we still have that same administration fee applied every for every application so we're trying to group them as much as possible with ones we already know and and hold off until the next batch is knowable and that's why it is unlikely that we're going to go after more funding like the lead service line funding until the machine learning information is uploaded because then we'll have another critical mass of numbers our hope is that at that point we're not we will not be limited by location in the in the sense that the earlier applications were based on put what they called neighborhoods areas that were in close proximity to each other we're hoping that we can just have a collection of lines that need to be replaced irrespective of the neighborhood that they're in which gives us a lot more flexibility it gives it allows it to be a less costly endeavor so we'd be borrowing less money to be
able to perform more of the work sure I just wanted to add that a piece of this as as director Campbell mentioned is that we are actually looking for grant funding for this so this is one of the few programs that pen best will offer grant funding with and one of the things that pen best has has recommended is that we look at specific neighborhoods because it helps us to increase our opportunities for grant funding and so some of the some of the reason that this is the 1.7 million and not more is because we're looking at some of these concentrated areas that he was talking about as well
And what is the expected timeline for receiving funding and completing these replacements? I don't know if I missed it.
No, you didn't miss it, and it's a couple of questions. One, by applying for this funding, we're hoping that the funds will be available by early 2026. we the the requirements of the program are at this moment that all lines must be identified and removed within approximately 10 years that has not yet changed but we understand that there may be some changes in policy under the
current administration but that is a request that mayors are bringing to the new administration regarding that timeframe of 10 years.
And I do want to emphasize that the City of Lancaster has had a— this is a spam call that people are just trying to get at me for— that the City of Lancaster has had a program for lead service line replacement for almost 15 years, and we've been replacing a small number of lead lines each year during that period. But with the mandate, we have to accelerate that program and with that mandate, which is unfunded, we must find the ways of doing it as a city, not as had been done previously.
And I just wanna underscore that we continue to treat our water to prevent lead leaching, which is in contrast to other communities that have had lead in their water and have not followed the proper protocols to reduce and eliminate lead leaching. So I always just want to underscore that. So this is a problem. And as you all heard me say before, we have more exposure to children becoming poisoned by lead through paint than we do because of a water source.
Thank you.
Thank you, Councilor Cleese. Any other questions or comments from members council from the public comment or question maybe council kind of
understands everything that's going on but as I come to these meetings and I hear about these resolutions it makes me want to ask more questions at the last council meeting we are approved to go for pen best I think for nine million dollars is that correct no okay yeah it was nine point one thank you Okay. Also, we just talked about two resolutions, number 25 and number 26, which totals like $5.6 million that would be going into the water, and I'm assuming some of these lead lines as well. We are now applying for $1 million, and I heard Mr. Campbell say it's grant or a loan i don't think that was clear i mean i would like to know if it is a grant or a loan what is the interest rate how low is it i also understand that they're going to be targeting neighborhoods and i know back when they first got the lead got money to do the lead lines they targeted the southwest and i remember coming to council and questioning while you're working on lead paint in the southeast why do you not focus in that area to get rid of all the lead so out of these 108 homes that would get done and they're targeting a neighborhood
do we know where that may be they're my questions a couple of those questions if you want me to um and i'm going to invite you so first part we don't know if we're going to get a grant or a loan yet this bird we have to apply okay and there's a certain amount of money that penvest has through the state revolving loan program and they evaluate based on the um criteria and need and so that goes to both the economic conditions in a particular neighborhood as well as our ability to identify that that is where lead lines are there are fewer known lead lines in the southeast than there are in the southwest that's why we're starting there additionally the total um but project over 10 years for the lead line replacement um director campbell steve i can't remember but we're in the we're above 10 million dollars of the total where are we
i can't remember i'm sorry we're assuming it's going to be between 12 and 15 million dollars what all told total at the value of the dollars in the respective years and so
that that is why we we don't know if we're even going to get any grant funding or if they're only going to have a lot of appropriate funds for a loan but we're just talking in this resolution we are just talking about about lead-mine replacement. The previous resolutions did not have to do with lead-mine replacements. They had to do with other infrastructure related to the 42-inch main, the membrane replacements, which is how to clean the water and the treatment plants, as well as the wastewater, which is completely separate. Those are two different things.
And if I may just add as well, since much of the utility infrastructure is very, very expensive, Penvest is the lowest loan rate that we can go after. Otherwise, we're looking at even bond financing, which often is more expensive over time. So we try to go after the funding that is least costly in order to do the work that is necessary.
That's why I didn't understand why I had to ask council meetings. We just went for $9 million. If we knew we were going to go from Penvest, I think they counted $9 million in the budget, if I'm correct. Why wasn't we asking for more when we got two more items of resolutions here? And we're paying administrative fees now for three applications when we just submitted one.
I'll let Director Tina Campbell respond to that.
Yeah, I'll just respond quickly with that one. So what we approved at the last meeting was for bond funding. So that was for funding that doesn't get the projects wouldn't be supported by a penvest. wouldn't be able to apply for them because they're not um eligible for pen best funding
so that's what we approved at the last one and i included nine million in that for from pen best
um no the what was approved was just the was just the bond um we talked about um some pen best funding that's coming up um but that has not been approved or or applied for at this point
it's not part of this are there uh any other questions or comments from the public hello again
uh tony dasher 700 block new holland avenue i don't have concerns as it relates to the immediate content of these but just you know i'm kind of reflecting on the bonds and this work that we need to do right now uh because ultimately these things increase the cost of living in lancaster in the long run the debt service obviously is incorporated into our taxes um the point or the thought running through my head rather i'm not 100 sure about this i'm just saying it for thought um you know i know the city at times throughout the years has um leveraged uh revenues from sewer or water to help balance the budget um and maybe it's worth because like in the charter we made it so you can't sell utilities maybe it's worth keeping those funds separate in the long run as well uh because you know i don't think anybody would have ever anticipated the pfa situation but maybe if water revenues had never been touched over the years there would have been more to pull from um so i'm not saying that as like a solid i think but i think it's worth looking into like keeping all these funds separate for the long run so that nobody throughout any because the this the debt situation for the city is something that occurs over a long period of time not just any singular person or council um so yeah that that's just what's been going through my head as we discuss these issues the idea of keeping uh sewer and water um their revenues separate and leaving them to those departments um in part because like one this is the need of life and you want to make sure the money's there but two we have customers outside of the city um so yeah those are just some
thoughts thank you mr gastro uh why are you thinking you don't need to comment but you've just created a four million dollar pool in the budget and the general fund budget that you would
then have to fill yeah i'm not talking about this year i'm i'm saying long long run and uh
director campbell just to clarify my point there the the funds that we use to pay for our water property tax our property tax bill that's our water bill is that correct
the funds we pay for our water are rate payers right here so including those non-city residents so the the debt service that for funds that are borrowed to do capital work in the in the water
fund or the wastewater fund is paid for by those rates just for clarification
the 42 inch main and membrane from the last administration was that ever
replaced the mayor made a comment on it so I'm reflecting towards her comment and she was just about to answer just making a point of order okay yeah because she was just
going to answer in your interjection the lead of the chair of public works we'll address that in
our next presentation okay the um 6 000 to 27 000 per line for uh the unit replacement and do you know what contractors were put on these or is that the cities those will be those will be competitively bid and because there are uh currently residents that are paying this amount because there were some homes that were done uh as far as the lead line and the replacements and these homeowners were affected by this cost and the city has yet to offer any type of you know you know anything to the homeowners could i speak to your question um i think part of this is to offer that assistance
um actually is to cover the cost of these 108 so that it's not the homeowner that is covering
that cost and also um yeah i'll just leave it at that okay but this has been ongoing conversations this is not something that you're presenting as a resolution today actually there was 7.1 million dollars that was received from a grant for this issue that's different or is the 9.1 along with the 7.1 million added to this funding that you're looking for no this is something
different and this is for the internal water service line inventory which is still the inventory is still taking place there hasn't been any replacement yet of the internal service line
correct thank you just just as a reference one may want to look on at the list of projects because it's very easy to confuse one penvest application request with another there is a list of projects i believe it's currently on the the project the list of projects for which the capital budget is supporting that we had submitted to council in previous meetings that's available I can confirm where it's available but I'll make sure that you all know where it is so that a link can be found so that one can take a look at the projects and the funding related to each of the respective projects there are dozens of projects in water dozens of projects in wastewater and a few projects in stormwater sorry I wasn't sure which
list you were talking about that's actually on our budget page on the
website so you can find it. Yeah, thank you. Question or comment from the public on resolution 27. Hearing none, I will make a motion to move resolution 27 to our full meeting of council on April 8th. Second. All those in favor? Aye. Okay, then the second and third PenVest resolutions relate to the water main transmission line project that Ms. Gomez had mentioned. I've talked about, we've talked about this at both the March 3rd and March 25th meetings and we discussed this in more detail in the fall as we talked about our capital plan this is a large project approximately 41 million dollars that is required because our water main coming from the Susquehanna water treatment plant is way past its useful life and we must have redundancy this this main supports over two-thirds of our water customers and this is the project that overlaid the bond funding in the graphs that we've provided to you on both March 3rd and March 25th. Penvest requires that a project be shovel-ready before we can apply for financing for the project. This project is still working through permits, design, etc., and in fact while we're trying to be conscientious of the costs, there have been some some adjustments over the last several months that confirmed less costly land acquisitions as necessary because this is a line that needs to go from the Susquehanna part of it is the line that goes from the Susquehanna water treatment plant to the oyster point reservoir however because of the deadline for a three million dollar grant that we have for this project as well as supply chain times we may pursue some interim bank financing until the project can be funded fully by pen vest and if necessary, Director Tina Campbell can speak to that. If we pursue this short-term financing, PennVest requires a resolution saying that our intent is to refinance the short-term financing with them. This is the third PennVest resolution. So the second PennVest resolution is requesting permission to make the application for the PennVest investment, and the third is committing that we would pay for any short-term finance that the intent is to refinance the short-term financing and that we would pay that.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Just a quick question. So the interim financing, is that being pursued due to the urgency of this particular project?
Part of it is to make sure that we have shovel ready and can move from one phase into the next phase without several-year interruption.
And is there an amount on that interim that the city might be seeking?
That's the three-month? That's the $27 million, sorry.
Yeah, so that would be about $27 million. We're not sure if we're going to need to pursue the interim financing yet or not, but it would be mainly for the pieces of equipment are needed or or actual pipe that's needed that would be supplied for the project so
that's that's critical at this moment for several reasons but the key reasons are that if you if one does not have the equipment or the material available everything comes to a halt the But the potential for supply chain interruption has been great since the advent of COVID. It has changed somewhat, but we may have different challenges as we go forward. But because it is a critical need, being able to purchase or have the ability to purchase the equipment and the materials for these eight miles or so of infrastructure would allow us to get the work, once the work gets started, we can move forward without interruption.
Sorry, we're playing a little tag team here. I did just want to add, Steve mentioned a $3 million grant. We do have a $3 million grant for this project that's been awarded. a deadline on that funding um and so that is another piece of this interim uh financing we would be able to use that three million to purchase some of this equipment um but getting
all of it is what we're looking at at this point thank you for that additional context um questions from full council or the committee the public works committee council president thank you
councillor um so we've been talking about the large diameter water baby replacement for quite some time director campbell can you just briefly talk about what phase we're in because i know we've been phasing this project because you mentioned it's eight miles of infrastructure
there are three phases and the numbering often gets confusing one phase is from the susquehanna river to the susquehanna water treatment plant that's that's the raw water bringing the raw water into the treatment plant the second part is bringing water from the susquehanna water treatment plant to the oysters oyster point reservoir that's the long distance line that's the steel line that has its useful life it's on paper useful life ended quite some time ago and we need to address that or else there's the potential and I don't want to I don't want to scare it we're not scared about this but there's a potential for a for a break that may create major problems that we don't want to to be dealing with as an emergency and that's why we were trying to do it this way and the third the third part is from the reservoir to the distribution system most of that part has already been completed or paid for and much of that is currently underway the the part from these from the river to the water treatment plant still needs some design and confirmation of sites for acquisition or for for playing with and then the the main part has largely been designed but we need to complete the design so that it is
actually shovel ready it can be bid as appropriate and I'm just taking kind of of also encapsulate the amount of work that this project takes. I'm assuming that there are endless permits with you mentioned permitting with other municipalities along the way, rights of way, easements, that sort of thing, like with every individual property owner.
Usually with most municipalities, we're trying to use existing rights of way to the extent practical, but sometimes it is private property, sometimes it is municipal property in a variety of different municipalities. Sometimes it's negotiating with Amtrak or other federal level infrastructure. Where we can share infrastructure, share existing infrastructure, we can usually keep the cost down somewhat. And so where we could identify lines or infrastructure and rights of way that can be shared, that's where we have, that's where we lean towards. That's what we try to negotiate.
Thank you. I just want to take a moment to reorient us in the project also appreciate the amount of work that has gone into planning to get us to just this point thank
you council president uh counselor matt uh thank you thank you uh director cannibal um counselor council president uh started kind of getting into the question i was going to ask but given that the water is used by other municipalities um are there any inner municipal agreements that he could try to negotiate where they could be putting up some of the costs or i i appreciate someone using some of the right public right away and everything but is there any way to go to the other municipalities and say you know can you help support this project in x way or we're going to raise rates for other municipalities by x amount so in principle yes the the rates are
different for outside outside city customers than they are for inside city customers but it is one water system one water utility which is a little bit different in concept than the wastewater which we are we share with a variety of partners and we need the consent of each partner every time we're doing infrastructure that affects the whole but in this case we would we've tried to find the the most effective cost effective uh least annoying way to get the work done and then then a different rate is charged to the internal rate payers than it is to the external rate payers.
Thank you, and I appreciate that. I would hope that the city isn't taking the majority of the burden. I understand we own the infrastructure, and it's a city asset, but I do feel that other municipalities should be stepping up and paying their fair share as well. So whether that's through rate changes to the PUC or whatever it may be, I think it's
forward that we think about that for the future we do work through the puc it needs to be puc approvable in all in all aspects whether it's external or internal rate payers we this is one reason it often takes as long as it does because we try to be as cost effective as possible and we explore uh alternatives that it may be costly to do the engineering to explore the different alternatives but it hopefully reduces the actual capital costs to all parties involved thank you councilman uh
thank you just a quick question and what impact what financial impact there is in on the waterways for the residents for the waterways rates for the rates this is part of
the presentations we've made over the last several months where the city of lancaster is about to undertake some major investments partly because of aging infrastructure partly in order to meet the requirements of the lead service line replacement which is an unfunded mandate partly because of the vagaries of addressing PFAS the forever chemicals and their prevalence in our in our water system in addition we're looking at leak detection so that we are reducing the amount of water treated water that we pay for that is escaping through leaks into the soil there's a lot of capital projects that we described both in the fall and in the and in the recent presentations that address a lot of these concerns for better or for worse this 40 some odd million dollar investment is in this in the scope of the larger investments that we're about to undertake over the course of the next several years in the moderate range and it's part of our what we call our our our ongoing restoration and investment work whether we had a consent decree for wastewater or not whether lead service lines existed or not whether pfos existed or not we would have to replace these lines um or else have risk an impingement on access to clean water in our water system and we're supplying water for 150 000 people so it is not an immodest expense it is an impactful expense and it is a necessary expense but it is not the most it's not the highest expenses that we're likely to encounter over the next several years i mean it
It will raise for the residents anyway, right?
Yes, it will. Both internal and external rate payers.
And this reimbursement, will it affect the city's overall debt?
Yes, it will. Do you want to speak to that, Tina? Yes, it will. Do you want to talk to how it will?
It is a loan, so it would be a part of the overall city debt
focused on the water fund just make sure I'm connecting the dots here piggybacking off a counselor that's question just to clarify city break hairs are disproportionately paying for this because the debt is paid by by repairs, water repairs, or?
Yes, please, because it's a good calculator.
No, so how the water rates work is that we do need to go to the PUC for any rate increases outside of the city. So I don't want to get into too many details of PUC rate cases. We're going for a PUC rate case now, so we're looking to increase external rates not internal rates at this time. Or at least that's the hope. PUC may require us to increase internal rates, but our goal is to look at external rates at this time. Once you put in a PUC rate case, you have to wait another 18 months, at least, in order to put in another one. And projects need to be completed before the PUC will consider them to increase the rate. And so our goal with timing of this to be able to put in a another puc rate case as soon as this project is complete um so the external customers would also see that increase um at that time so we pro or we look at rate
increases considering these projects and the debt costs of that and the rate increases for both internal and external correct correct yeah thank you for that clarification are there any other
Any other questions from the Council or the Public Works Committee?
Any questions or comments from the public?
We're talking about both Resolutions 28 and 29, is that correct? Or are we just talking about 20? Okay, so we're talking about two. Okay, so I think Council, I think you're all asking the right questions. I do believe that no one's trying to say this is not a need. We understand the water. home rule can explain a lot to me so I do have a clear understanding about that the question is how we're financing it and that's what council needs to be a concerned about and councilman LeChard I appreciate your asking the impact on the residents because that's what council needs to be concerned about we're talking about borrowing 27 million that we will pay back on bonds that we already approved if and I understand the process that we need to have this work shovel ready then that means we jump the gun to borrow the money on the bonds because this process has to happen first and that's what council needs to be looking at because one of the things are we understand we already approved the bonds but now to say we're going to go get another loan for 27 million just so we can be ready to spend the money that we get from the bonds so that the project shovel ready and then we're going to take the money that we get from Penvest I guess and the bonds and pay this 27 million back so this is going to be like a short-term loan but in the process we're paying interest on that so I think council needs to get into the financing and not look into who's saying we need this water line and everybody understands the stormwater everybody well maybe they don't understand it but the need is there we know the city is old we understand the epa we understand what's going on with our water but the fact that our water rates and things are going to go up is a result of council approving borrowing money when it's sitting and we're not using it and we're paying interest on it now we're this week we're talking about getting a loan on the money that we just borrowed to put us in more debt so i think you know you need to make sure that you understand exactly what we're doing because this is a greater
impact on the homeowner and the taxpayer i could just say i hear your concerns and frustrations miss bird i think that the way that this is set up is that we have to borrow the money send the money put the projects in the ground and then go for rate increase to then pay ourselves back and when we go to the puc we're never i don't think ever have gotten 100 of what we requested And so it is an upside-down process, and that is something that we have talked about in terms of effectuating change at the state level with how the PUC does this. But they are also there as a means of protecting rate payers, specifically those who are not represented by the city council who live outside of the city. So they are there specifically to prevent any kind of price gouging or raising of rates unfairly, but the rules are the rules and we have to spend the money first before we can get the rate increase, which goes to your point about where are we borrowing this money from and how are we expeditiously getting the products in the ground. and i think those are the questions that continue that council should continue to ask especially because we're going to be putting timelines um for projects on our capital plan that we'll be presenting to you in june and so those are the things that you should be monitoring because the bond funds i will say very clearly historically the city has not been good about getting projects in the ground utilizing bond funds and that's been a legacy that has been from you know previous administrations that we are trying to change and part of that starts with having a capital plan and a really clear sequence of what we need to borrow for what projects and in what sequence and not taking off not biting off more than we can chew because the list of projects that was originally presented was much longer than the one that you got thank you mayor is that fair that's
very fair thank you counselor related to that and director campbell you can just confirm additionally puc rate cases take a long time it's my understanding that from the time you actually request the rate case it's typically about nine months to maybe not get all that you would ask for so i imagine that that planning is also that just makes the planning all that more difficult and
also projects to get done even more timely yes it's the timing is critical not only in terms of getting it started and completed but in order for us to anticipate the the next borrowing if it's a subsequent phase to get done that work needs to get done within the 9 to 18 months that it may take for that approval.
Thank you.
Are there any other questions or comments from the public?
Yeah, so I understand that the PUC have deadlines and their projects need to be completed. So because we can't meet the deadlines, because projects are not being completed, this is where we are. There are, you mentioned, 150,000 people that are accessing this water. there's about 60 000 people in the city of lancaster as residents what measures are you using to pursue the townships and counties that are receiving water from us because we should not be the only ones held accountable to pay this like are you have you sent out requests have you sent out any type of uh formal made meetings with the townships to um bring in bring forth any type of
revenue on their part sorry it's a very fair question but it's the nature of a puc the public utility commission establishes for our water system not only the rates but the the means by which infrastructure investment can be we can be compensated or reimbursed and we cannot make changes to those we have to work alongside and within the limits of the PUC limit or requirements and legal limitations it does as the mayor had indicated allow for the reimbursement which is via the rate increases that take place independently there's rate increases at the exterior which we've proposed for this year for the exterior ratepayers which is hopefully going to be paying for part of that interest for what we borrow in the short term until it gets installed and accepted at which point the PUC after the nine to 18 months can say yes that is a provable and therefore reimbursable and then we would enter into either another rate case for the inside rate payers and or outside rate payers as well so it is kind of a seesaw but to your point we're within the limits of and we're run by the PUC the regulations of the PUC in terms of how we access money from outside but it's a very very good question a very important question to the conversation the other question
is when you when you just for the record is the Public Works Committee present today because you keep mentioning that like who's on the Public Works Committee
is it just mr. Campbell and how many are in the
committee just just the three of you okay yeah and then you had mentioned you were going to refi the first short-term financing are you saying that there is already a loan in place that you're looking to request or pursue this funding to refinance what is already in place can you clarify that so the
short-term financing would be as as needed and that would be refinanced to the pen vest loan which is the administration resolution number 28 once that pen best loan is ready to be to be funded so it is already can you if you
have a question you just ask it in the mic no she answered okay are there any other questions
um diane desmond i live off route 30 near the state police um i wanted to just give you a little bit of scope of um what i'm currently dealing with in my apartment community um we saw from 2020 to sorry from 2024 to 2025 a 67% rate increase on our water bill and I'm not going to blame all of that on these very necessary projects because I understand that that could be price gouging from my apartment complex however just because there was such a drastic rate increase and that's something that we like directly feel in our pockets what range of increase should we as citizens anticipate for these projects and when do you predict We may see those increases hit our bills Yeah, I'm like right next to the State Police Okay, thank you
Thank you so much. I think that's right.
Any other question or comment from the public on resolution 28 or resolution 29? Hearing none, I'm going to move these together to our full meeting of council on April 8th. So again, all those in favor? Aye. Thank you so much. The only thing I just want to say about, you know, it's not lost on us what the impact is going to be to customers and i think that's why you know i'll just speak from my perspective as someone that works in government finance a lot of it comes down to figuring out okay where the funds what are they eligible to be used for and you kind of have to game them in a certain way to get the best outcome and i think part of this process is you know we're issuing bonds but then we're also going for a penvest loan which my understanding is that we could finance that at a lower rate uh director tina camel's waving her head yes then you know a bond and then we also have grant applications which actually is what we're going to get into now but i'm only just emphasizing to say that it's it's a capital mix there's a mixture of different funding sources that are going into each of these these products um but with that i do want to talk about these grants so uh director campbell do you want to talk about resolution number 30. yes resolution number
30 is authorizing the filing of an application for funding through the department of conservation and natural resources dcnr that's a state entity community conservation partnership program in the amount of one point three eight five zero three five million i'm not sure if if what you have says 900 000 or 1.385 million what i had as of actually now i think we got an updated one in the second email yeah okay so the 1.385 is the is the correct one we anticipate that this is for south end park we anticipate the south end park will cost approximately 2.7 million dollars total dcnr limits us to asking for 50 and that's what the what the request is for here we are anticipating um the match being from local partly from local shares which we've applied for separately under to the tune of approximately one million dollars um it is there is a proviso since we're just making an application there's a chance that we don't get all that we've been asked for or that we're asking for they will tell us if we're not going to be eligible for the full amount and we would be able to consent to either accepting the lower amount or not doing the project or changing the project all together but this this is asking for permission to make the
application thank you director campbell uh and i'll just add it's written in the resolution text what some of these improvements will be they include upgrades and playing them in services modeling purpose field basketball court upgrade improve ada access water planning fencing improve lighting and seating it's just some of the things that we hopefully will see happening at south end
parks and I will say that this is one of the more creative endeavors that we've done recently partly as a result of the parks and recreation open space master planning process but then separate consultants that worked with the community in different ways and we've worked with them in the past where people's ideas were were pasted together there's actually a small skating skate park as well as uh roller park for for small bicycles etc so they've been able to to maximize the utility of the south end park for active recreation as well as passive recreation
thank you um i'll open it up to questions or comments from the public works committee or
full council anything from the public that's a very good question i'm not sure
do you know where it is it's it's it ended up being a little bit larger than we expected based on the setbacks on the site as well as vegetation that could be relocated to be able to make use of active recreation and this skate park area but I can get you the precise and in fact it's on the engage Lancaster
website that's about right 1.2 acre what we're here 1.2 acres oh correct it's not
a huge park it's certainly nothing like reservoir or we muster or Buchanan but we are able to pack a lot of in very interesting activities in even that
smaller area do you want to come to the so the one point three eight is for both
the south end and Reservoir Park or just enough okay and how much is it for the
we're not talking about that one yet okay okay yeah so I could just mention you had mentioned that people's ideas are in order to cut waste or cut funding or try to save as much are you using city residents workers skilled workers Thaddeus Stevens you know people that are actually and you know in the city that can do these for less costs in terms of looking for contractors, bidders, because it's been known that we're wasting a lot of money and funding on taxpayer dollar to recruit outside of the city of Lancaster to do these projects, which take time because commuters don't have the time to get in here at 6 a.m., 7 a.m. to start projects. And we see them leaving at 3.30 p.m. when they should be leaving at normal business hours. So for these projects as a whole and as a city, you know, can we, can you have some type of consideration to utilize the residents of the city of lancaster who are in training in thaddeus stevens graduates you know um skilled workers there's multiple skilled workers we took pride in our city uh when we built i've been here 30 years the residents have always taken pride in their city in community parks in upgrading and cleaning and doing everything we're seeing more outsiders coming into our city that are costly it's very cost effective a lot of them don't pay taxes here you are burdening the residents on these projects that we can cut costs on and it's shameful that we continuously have to go outside of the city of lancaster with 50 60 000 residents and say that there's no one here that can take this bid for a cheaper price it's it's not fair you know what i mean we took we take pride in building our city it's always been like that since the 50s 40s you know use the people here so that these costs can be substantiated left or lessened i'm just asking for consideration well as you may know
we do have a relatively extensive self-performance part of our work much of our paving is self-performed we can perform 34 to 50 percent more paving because we self-perform rather than contract out as a value engineering effort we can look at what parts of any of the parks whether it's this park or any park that we're looking for funding for can be done as self-performance it does not mean that self-performance is done without without any expense it does mean a different level of of administration oversight of purchasing materials etc but generally speaking parts of projects can be done as self-performance the challenge with working with with uh working with uh thaddeus stevens or with other organizations is putting in place a a longer term program which is not off the table but a long-term program that not only supports skill sets but skill sets that are transferable into their workforce work experience as well as you know fatty Stevens currently has a design and work program where the students actually build affordable housing in different parts of the city that's where they're supervised by journeymen or journey people who are overseeing the work to ensure that it meets the construction and design and construction standards of the building industry it often is there are there are trade-offs in doing it that way but there some of the trade-offs may be appropriate trade-offs but I think I take your point that if if we're not able to find not only if we're not able to find local contractors but if the costs are excessive or if we're not getting all the funding that we're looking for and we still want to perform this park that's those are options that can look at joe jackson park for instance is an example where we're more likely to do most of that park with our own source resources in order not only to keep the cost down but also to stay on
on a schedule that's accelerated thanks for that additional context director cameron i'm glad you mentioned the houses that steven's uh students built because i just passed the one they are building currently on a hillside the other day and it's um you know i remember when that came to us and to see if it builds uh it's me um are there any other questions or comments from the public on resolution 30. hearing on i'll make a motion to move resolution 30 to our full meeting
of council on april 8th so all those in favor aye and then last and possibly least this is the request for an application for funding through through again dcnr for uh community conservation partnership in the amount of 74 960. i'm hoping that you had that amendment as well to be used for the master planning of reservoir park we expect the master planning effort to be approximately 150 000 this is a 50 grant request and we fully expect that that will be um be able to come through but the request is for us to have the permission to make the application thank you
director campbell are there any uh questions or comments from the public works committee
the request is for 74 490 960 rather and the total cost is anticipated at 149. thank you
thank you for your remarks and just real quick question uh this is for the master plan this
isn't for the actual improvements that is correct so the nature of master planning is that it means reaching out to the community which has been as i understand it and please correct me if i'm wrong has been hungry for this work to be done for several years anyway but things have changed throughout the city it's also the best probably best location for fairground park it has not only very mature trees but it also has a subsurface a substrate that allows for playground equipment and for carnival equipment on a temporary basis it's also part of the East End community small area plan so there's ideas that are being generated in terms of what the recreational needs are for this particular community in large as well as trying to be consistent with the the Parks and Recreation master plan which identified local neighborhood and regional needs to be to be met so it's an opportunity for we reaching out to the community engaging them hopefully in in as dynamic a manner as we have with the south end park and others so that it can address the concerns and the needs that are addressed that need to be addressed today not in the last parks
and recreation master plan I just want to agree with mr. Campbell when he said
about the needs changing and I'm wondering if we're not jumping the gun on Reservoir Park as far as we're planning because as you know the county prison is going to become a different place at a different site so what will the need be for Reservoir Park and when that happens and are we willing to go back and reinvest more money and to come up with a plan now for 1.49 million dollars which is just a plan knowing that there's going to be other changes one of the things I want to encourage council is there is no such plan for a park in the southeast area and I think if we're going to talk about putting a park we have this location behind jackson middle school where the community has engaged and has spoken loud and clear that's what we would like to see there our park and we're just looking for council to come up with a plan to say well let's see what we can do here i mean we keep here and we're spending millions and millions of dollars in the parks we do have some top lots in the southeast area but we do not have a park in the southeast area so i just say don't jump the gun for reservoir park in your planning on what it's going to be like because as the county prison comes on that whole block that need may change and we don't want to invest in something and then we're turning around and borrowing more money or seeking other grant money to change it thank you thank you
yeah and i just want to piggyback on that because i have been asking the mayor since she first took this position um that my concern was reservoir park we talked about this in the beginning of her becoming mayor so there are specifically you know things such as the playground so I don't know if it was seven eight years that she's that you have been mayor but I've been asking for the playground and I know it's not going to cost one point something million dollars just to do the playground the pool is okay I don't know what's gonna happen with taking away you know what was there which was the arena the hockey arena it was dismantled completely it could have been used for something else like the children playing baseball you know they there's teams that are associated with schools and they don't have a turf to play in you know I think Reservoir Park would have been excellent because there was stools there I mean there was you know it was a whole hockey arena all you had to do is basic improvements to take it down completely is depriving the children from usage and it's just sitting there for years but nothing it's just an empty space so I understand that did he you said 1.49 million for reservoir 149,000 that plan for 140 you said 150,000 do you have specifics like you were very specific hearse when you said the basketball field you know when we were talking about the South Bend Park you were very specific can you give me specifics on what the 150,000 would be for on reservoir park the design so
this is a master planning effort it's not the design effort the master planning effort means reaching out to the local community to adjacent neighbors to others who may may use the park for whatever reasons they might want to and identify what is of interest to them what are the space requirements for that what are the noise implications of some of that are there aspects of the Parks and Recreation Open Space Master Plan that need to be recognized because it because it is such a centrally located park in principle because it has special characteristics such as being available as a fairgrounds type park where no other park in the city has that availability without making major damage how does one make use of that and so similar to the processes that got us from conception to more detailed design for Southend Park and others it would be inviting the community at whatever level to come in and describe what's important to them what's interesting to them hopefully it would be a series of meetings so that people can share their ideas and the consultants would come back several times to say this is what we heard you say is this what you what you actually mean and how do we put something that takes up this kind of space which might be a ball field adjacent something that takes up this kind of space which might be a skate park if those are the types of things that in consensus that community believes are appropriate so the master planning effort is to is to generate the ideas as you as you're talking about because you've presented several different ideas and many other people may have other ideas as well that they think may be appropriate for them and their their own families but it would not be the specific design it would be making sure that here are programmatically ways that these kinds of spaces can fit in this kind of a location I do want to say that it will be done a bit later in the process than the anticipated schedule for the for the south end for the east end small area plan in the sense that that's currently underway and so some ideas may still be generated from that which would be able to be talked about on the table but not be ruled by it the city the prison is a county site and what we want with it maybe I should ask Chris to speak but But what we're hoping is going to happen with the East End Small Area Plan is community-based ideas on what can and should happen at that site that might influence decision-making at the county level, whereas Reservoir Park is ours, and that's something that we can be making decisions on rather sacrosanct within the limits of that park.
southeast plan, we are aware that the prison and reservoir is in the southwest, correct? So when we're asking for a plan for the southeast of Lancaster, we're not talking about the southwest. I mean, every, if you look at every quadrant, you have a plan for the city. Reservoir, and I think the plan that I saw on the southeast plan includes reservoir, the prison, and then some of the southeast area. So it's both southwest and southeast.
Are there other questions or comments for the public on
Resolution 31? I just want to say one thing. Sorry. Just real quickly, just as far as plans in the reservoir park and, you know, getting the folks involved and the residents, I've been living there for 30, well, 20 something years. I've bought my house in 99. So I want to certain that we are very the community in Reservoir Park area we're very informed we have a neighbors engagement you know it's a it's it's it's all we're very active together so we know what we want we've been stressing our opinions for quite some time so it's not like you know we don't know what we want and it's been shared with the mayor to like primarily the park itself because they opened it up to um i don't want to say how do you without offending anyone offenders child offenders live there in the houses that is close by reservoir park and they come into the park and they do things and they leave things that we continuously have to clean up and they write all over that it's it's old the the play yard is old it needs to be reconstructed so that was our major concern for the last eight years they put in a pool they put in the wheels the bike wheels I mean there's a lot of improvements in the park but as far as maintaining that park you know fixing the grass adding you know the beauty in the the park it's not being done we as a community we have to do it ourselves even if it's cleaning up stuff on the floor so yeah we were just more concerned about picking up a needle when our kids are going down a slide and making sure that it's cleaned and and maybe taping up cracks within the actual set the plate the plate unit set and yeah so it's safe for the kids to go down so it's it's old it needs replaced thank
you Tony that's just 700 block in New Holland Avenue I don't have a problem with us approving the grant application I think it's worth applying for and seeing where it goes but I do think that miss Byrd is making a good point about parks in the southeast in general i think miss gomez is as well um you know and i want to just kind of maybe say a good thing is we could potentially use this program to fund those sort of parks in the future um so i you know i think it's worth the city applying for the grant i do also have some level of reservation because of the planning that needs to occur with the prison but i understand you're working from the frame of reference you have right now and i think this is a very reasonable thing to do thank you mr duff are there other comments or questions
hearing none i will make a motion to move resolution 31 to a full meeting council in april all those in favor aye aye and that concludes the public works committee thank you very much
thank you councillor hirsch uh we will now go to the community planning committee councillor craig
Thank you, Council President. Community planning has one item on the agenda this evening. It's administration bill number 3-2025 authorizing the sale of real property. And that's me,
Councilor Craig. Thank you. Currently, the ordinance sets forth how we are able to sell property in the city of Lancaster, and that is through two options, either by a sealed bid or through public option this administrative bill three would authorize the sale of real property through a third method which is through a licensed real estate broker and so I would call your attention to this section in the ordinance that specifies that if we were to do this that council would approve the process for how we select the real estate agent, et cetera, et cetera. So that, I believe, is spelled out in the ordinance that was provided to council. So this is really a way that we can utilize our home rule status to effectuate change, to make more efficient how we do certain things. and um that's the gist of this uh bill in front of you for consideration thank you mary i'm curious
to know what was the the process before was that we would do a resolution and and said and then once we went and got into the beginning of january that allowed us the abilities to change the the
way that we did it before was always council approved the sale of a property what this piece of legislation is doing is not changing that what it is doing is adding a method for how we can sell a piece of property that council approves to be sold home rule the thing that changed about home rule is that it gives us flexibility where we don't where we're able to have flexibility to sell real property and that can now be using a real estate agent which means that it's the property gets listed on an MLS listing that more people see it that other Realtors can talk to their clients about the product they're working on and not just rely on an ad in the Sunday paper that says that we're accepting bids
yeah would counsel still have to approve the methodology if there was a property
that the city wanted to sell or is that to the administration to determine which route they want to go to sell the property I it is my understanding and I
have to actually go back and check I have to read it again because I read it a day ago and I'm just not sure that I'm a hundred dollars but what I think is that when we bring the council property or or want to change how we have a property for sale we would need to get a council's approval for this method and then there's a process for our selecting realtor and all of that stuff I think
great just for the next meeting if we could just have that yeah i think it's in the ordinance if
you read the ordinance i think it's there i'm just i haven't read it in a day so i don't want
to misspeak thank you mary so currently i mean the way it's it's right here i think it's number three it would provide compensation to be paid to the real estate broker is that what we're doing
currently or it says the addition to i'm trying to find it in the list of 17 attachments one second
um it's right after section right below section one yeah i have to find that oh thank you chris
a handout yes um so right now we're not paying a real estate broker because we can't use a real estate broker exactly did i did that answer your question counselor so why would we so but right
here it's stating that by changing it the person will be able to negotiate and we would have to
compensate the real estate agent is that or broker yes we would pay a real estate broker for their
work for their services currently yeah we do the same no we do currently we're precluded from using a real estate broker exactly thank you very much that's what i needed to know okay councilman
craig maybe this would help us as well typically typically uh realtors get paid once the sale of the property is complete they're not paid prior to okay so i would imagine that would happen in this
situation so it uh upon recommendation of the mayor city council may by resolution authorized that specific parts of real property be sold for the use of a licensed real estate broker so that we would be bringing to you a resolution that would authorize the use of a real estate broker that resolution must authorize the same which would provide the terms conditions and basis uh which is uh point number one number two provide who has authorization to negotiate an offer and accept an offer submitted to the city uh three i'm paraphrasing here provide for the compensation to be paid to the broker and required according to city council is number four uh and five set for the time frame during which offers of sale may be solicited for such a property by the licensed real estate broker so all of this would be part of a resolution that
would come to council when we wanted to use a realtor questions from the council as a whole
Thank you, Councilor Craig. I know this is the first reading, and this is just a committee, but I do have some questions around what the process would look like, the selection of the realtor. Also, I understand it would expand the possible market for a property to be sold, but I do think that there might be, I mean, real estate is a very competitive market, um and i just have some questions around how you decide which realtor you know that wouldn't you know and i know this i mean maybe these are some questions we can talk about at the next meeting as
well but yeah i will say that like the redevelopment authority of the city of lancaster has a realtor um the board hired them uh and i we can find out more information about that process i i think that this is step one and there would be a follow-up step that i mean we would certainly bring back to a process for how we do that but we do procurement on a regular basis to hire people with expertise in different areas and so i imagine we'd issue a request for proposals and that candidates is the same way we do when we hire consultants to provide engineering or
financial support whatever we do yeah I think that was one of my questions would this be a city appointed real estate firm that does all of the real estate sales or would it just be every single time we want to sell a property it's just open to all realtors I think that for the sake of efficiency we'd probably hire someone for a period of time but also the city doesn't have a lot of real estate that it's trying to sell on a regular basis
so we don't um and we don't i don't think that uh that that would be um a thing ongoing i will say that for for this uh this is really born out of the lack of interest in station six property that property received one sealed bid response and i did not feel that that was significant sufficient uh to only have one response and so this is a way to get more responses yeah i just
i guess i would just hope that we would still have the ability of the intention of what that property
becomes that's also through a whole zoning process and so um and that information that we've collected related to zoning uh for that particular parcel would be part of the sale and typically sales of properties in the city of langley lancaster are contingent have contingencies related to them getting zoning approval for anything that they would use the product for which is the opportunity for the public to weigh in if they don't like the concept that's being there and so we would likely sign a sales agreement that would be contingent upon them getting the approvals that they need and if they don't get them then the property wouldn't be sold
that is a very standard practice thank you and that answers some of my questions but i look
forward to discussing this yeah if you want to send a follow-up um counselor ahmed of other questions that you have i'll make sure to get that out to council before our next meeting so you have that information my questions are there any further questions from council as a
Yes, Darlene Bird. I think council needs to be very cautious in what they're doing. I think this goes under an administration code. I think to once you put that in place as one of the things you would be deciding is who has the authority to make those decisions. So if it becomes the administration, then council, it's not in your hand. I think that number one, we would need to looked at a list of properties that the city has. Number two, we have a record of changing things for one thing. I understand it's Station 6 that we are trying to get rid of. And we in the city have a very good habit of changing how we do business for one thing, and it doesn't work out always. For instance, zoning, especially when came to the um air and b or you know short rooming houses changed in one meeting and we changed it again because it didn't work i think council needs to be very cautious i do understand about the station six i think there's there are other means out there i do think that we all know that once the city would sell our property and it goes before zoning the zoning is picked by council and the mayor so why wouldn't you you know they always have that option of appealing or look seeking a variance to have it changed to do what they want i mean if we're not putting stipulations in the deed on what that property can become i think we do lose what you were asking about councilman ahmed i would also like to see a list of properties that the city owns and maybe any that they are considering selling i mean maybe at this time it's only that one But we all know once we give up that power from council to the administration, you don't come back to it. And I think this was set aside in the home rule under the administration code that you can put back. I don't think it was set from home rule to say this is something that we want. I think one of the things that you need to understand about home rule is that the administration has to come up with an administration code on how we function and a lot of things that we asked about in the home rule was going to be addressed through the administration code which council has to adopt i don't think we got there yet so to put stuff in now when that has not been adopted is jumping the gun i mean slow down take some time it's not something that needs to happen now at this moment thank you i'll just add it's a
fair point that this is part of the administrative code moving forward and it is true that i'm i am presenting this and i asked our solicitor presented us because this is a real property that council has already approved the sale of and that we have not been successful selling there is no authority related to the sale property that the administration gets without council approval uh and so i want to just make that clear um and the the other piece is that um all of the council all of the city properties mr you can find them on uh by doing a query on building blocks and you can see all of the properties that are owned by the city parks all of the buildings etc there is no plan at this time to sell any additional property we just want to sell this one that council approved last year that we still have not sold and just and just
um in reference even when we talked about the redevelopment authority when we're um they're taking people's homes they don't just give it to the they have a realtor that comes out to sell it and different people get to bid on it so keep that in mind so this is city property that we own
so I would keep that in mind yes and it is a competitive market um and there are a lot of programs not being used for first-time homebuyers and there are a lot of families that could use properties across the city that is being taken by bidders there's a reason why the city precluded this from or from using real estate agents there is a reason why so I want you to really really look at what we're saying because it's very very important decisions cannot be reversed and a lot of citizens residents in Lancaster are very much affected by this administration because of changes so I want you to think about that really good, especially our children and grandbabies. Tony Dasher, 700 block of New
Holland Avenue. So this is concerning to me because the way I see this is as creating a method of private sale for public goods. There is a reason I think the bidding process is in place and there is, as far as I understand, there's nothing prohibiting us from being more open about our advertising. We're just required to advertise in the newspaper general circulation this should not be the way we handle this because when you use a realtor I mean I recognize the argument like it's valid you do open up the potential for a transaction to occur but you also channelize those communications you don't ensure that this is an open transparent public process for the whole public and I understand that it is arduous to try and sell a property I frankly do not think we should sell station six I think there are other solutions to do with station six but I'm generally frustrated in right now us putting forward amendments like this or this is an administration bill but this a recent zoning amendment that was not presented at the last meeting because there's some pause elsewhere but just expressing a frustration I have when we the city Planning Commission weren't made aware of the disapproval or at least I wasn't I I've listened to the meeting twice and it wasn't discussed that that zoning amendment had been disapproved and I feel like what we're working through right now is a bunch of ad hoc things and we need to focus on these bulk products like the entire zoning code and the entire administration code I think we're moving too fast I think that there are valid questions if you had about this process because it could be exclusionary to the public and create solutions that the whole public does not feel confidence in because a realtor could reach out to somebody and sell somebody on a dream that the public doesn't want doesn't the use might be allowed but it doesn't mean that it's something that the public's looking forward to so I do think the bidding process is the one we should stick with at this current moment in time I as a resident am open here hearing about other alternatives potentially like this in the future but I think this this is a this is a big shift from the way government's supposed to operate this is this is trying to operate government
like a business and government should operate like a government it was disapproved by this County Planning Commission my apologies no they they
approved Planning Commission approved I'm just expressing the frustration we
weren't made aware of that at Planning Commission okay I will just say that you know we are planning to bring the first tranche and I think Councillor Mead reported on this as part of his transition committee report that we're going to plan to bring the first tranche if an admin code changes to council in June followed successfully in August September time frame with the second tranche this can wait until i am really just trying to fulfill the wishes of this body that you want to sell we collectively decided that that was what the need was so it's fine post another public bid then we shouldn't
change the process just yet and pausing this three months we we need to have bigger community community conversation about the idea of changing these public processes thank you that's what we're
we're here for. Thank you. I just want to add, I just want to add real quickly, there are non-profit organizations such as churches, multiple, a substantial amount of churches throughout the city of Lancaster that could use that. That is true. And we could, and they're not being, I work with multiple churches. We could decide. You're not reaching out to them. We could give it
away and at the same time I would say that we're also trying to pay for a lot of things this is a conversation about the future use of this parcel there there was no we sent it out to every housing organization in the city that had been doing work there were no proposals that came from any housing nonprofit housing organization in the city because they have a lot of projects as they're currently working on and so there wasn't there wasn't any interest there was a commercial use that was proposed that was not a public use and it was one bid and so just to say there was a lot of effort that was put into getting this out to our nonprofit partners there was conversation about sale prices I mean all of that could be negotiated uh in terms of a use that was in um that the neighborhood would be excited about that council would be excited about the administration would be excited about that would go through zoning um and that just didn't come to bear and i don't think it's because of lack of interest i think it's because of lack of resources at this particular moment a lot of the organizations have really big projects that they're already working on with arpa funds that they need to complete and some of those projects haven't even started yet
and the city is in desperate need of a low-income subsidized housing and I don't think that HUD or the Housing Authority would be more than happy to grab this to put some housing for the people in the city of Lancaster they are desperate there's more and more homeless people out there so I don't think you're drawing the right audience so I'll take that into consideration good evening me
again I live off 30 Diane Desmond yes Diane Desmond hi so I just wanted to further urge council to consider when you're looking at this proposal to consider a checks and balances system to ensure that current residents are prioritized over profit I know that it looks like a very lucrative opportunity but there could be some very real consequences for the current residents the city um and i also would urge you to consider how this could potentially exclude voices of the
public in this process of what happens in their own city thank you since this is a bit with the full council for consideration for the eighth second all those in favor all right thank you council president planning has this evening thank you very much calendar craig uh the last committee
this evening is the committee of the whole we have three items on our agenda this evening uh counselors the first is resolution number 24 2025. this is all raising a flag raising to mark the reagan heritage month an application has been made in a timely manner uh for a flag raising um and this is i had it in front of me and i accidentally closed it during the course of our meeting and i apologize um an application was put in i'm totally missing who submitted the application it doesn't say it which is why i missed it i apologize the request was put into uh Puerto Rican flag or do the i'm sorry the late hour is getting to me to raise the Puerto Rican flag in honor of uh part of nope uh on i'm sorry November 18th 2025 with the rain date of November 19th 2025. thank you very much uh and this was actually uh requested by council Jamie Roy thank Okay. Thank you. I'm sorry. I'm a little loopy. It's been a very long day and I appreciate that. So anyway, this is to raise the Puerto Rican flag on the date of November 18th in front of City Hall. Council, any comments on the resolution? Comments from the public on the resolution? Ms. Gomez.
Just one quick question. November 18th through the 19th, is that like a marked date representing anything in the history of Puerto Rico that we can raise it on that date, or can you accept a more historical date?
Councilor Arroyo, this date was chosen for a particular reason?
Yeah, typically that week is considered National Puerto Rican Week.
Okay, that's what I wanted to know. Thank you.
Yep, and so the date of the flag raising will be the 18th, and we're reserving the 19th for a rain date. Any additional comments from the public? Hearing none, I will make a motion to move Resolution No. 24 to our next council meeting on the 8th.
Second.
A motion and a second. All those in favor? Aye. Any opposed? Thank you. Next item on our agenda for Committee of the Whole is Council Resolution No. 23-2025. recognizing April a sexual assault awareness month in the city of Lancaster this is an annual resolution of recognition that I am presenting we typically invite folks from our YWCA sexual assault prevention center to come to council to address and talk about any current events they have going on for the month statistics and information that's pertinent to city residents and it's important that we note this every year any council comments on this resolution from the public hearing now making motion that we move council resolution 23 2025 to our next meeting on the 8th second motion and a second all in favor aye any opposed and lastly we have have resolution number 32, 2025, recognizing Lafayette and Lancaster bicentennial. This is an interesting historical resolution. This is a resolution designating July 27 through the 29 as Lafayette days in the city of Lancaster in recognition of the bicentennial of Lafayette's visit to Lancaster on his farewell tour 50 years after the American Revolution. There are many events happening around the city and also at Rockford for this event. And this would make this an official designation in the city of Lancaster for this historic event. Any additional council comments on the resolution from the quickly dwindling public? Hearing none, I'll make a motion to move this to council on our April 22 meeting.
Second. Second.
All those in favor? Aye. you very much um that is the end of our committee agenda mr harris you've submitted your clerk's report in writing is that correct i have madame president thank you that's available to all members of council uh having concluded our business i'll hear a motion to adjourn I heard a motion. I heard a second in there. Thank you very much. All those in favor? Aye. Thank you. We're adjourned.